how man it's just such a beautiful
notion of thinking about this idea of
faith as being groundedness being
solidity as being oriented the word the
word faith having a fundamentally
agentic yeah like turning in the word
meaning like the move moving it from the
semantic domain into the nursing of
means to an end right into the faith has
something about that which is has a as a
well-founded reliable means to an end
mmm-hmm yeah it's so funny maybe think
about it like if you if you kind of
transposition in that direction a like a
basketball player mmm a truly masterful
basketball player you've seen certain
circumstances when they shoot a shot and
they just turn around and walk away
because they know well before the ball
is hit the hoop that it's going in yeah
that's faith yeah it's the faith of the
master knowing that their tool will do
with the tool is intended that their
will will carry itself out in the world
with artistry and a certain elegance
because the competence is just there
like they just know that feels to me
like that's getting in the right
direction how's that landing for you I
like parts of it and I want to I want to
sort of open up other parts of it
because the thing that concerns me and
what you said let me say what concerns
me and then let me say what I liked what
landed for me what concerns me is part
of that historical narrative was also
the shift with Luther right and you get
the shift towards sort of willful
assertion that and that God is also a
purely willing agent willing in the
sense not of wanting but of actively
enforcing his will on the world the
imposition position notion mmm-hmm yeah
and so and and we know some of the
dangerous offshoots of this which is the
idea of faith has sort of
you know almost a magical will
imposition of your will on the world
you'll just sort of will the world to be
what you want it to be and and I don't
think you want to put your finger on
that I don't think you want to say that
because I know what we discussed before
yeah so so there's so let me be thrown
in front of the Met where that comes to
my mind as you're talking and they both
have to do with water so one has to do
with the notion of a kayak in the river
the other one is a surfer on a surfboard
yeah yeah and I think there's a really
big distinction between a surfer who
really has this sense that he is going
to out paddled the ocean you know his
will is the thing right that it's a
matter of almost like a brutal forcing
of mastery on the natural environment
the ocean is a great example because in
most cases this just straight up isn't
gonna happen to be a good surfer it's
first and foremost you've learned that
lesson that primarily your
responsibility is sensitivity to be
aware of the flows that you're enmeshed
in right right and there's something
about your choice he's like a trim tab
in the in the Bucky fuller sense there
there's a there's an opening as a pun
there's a place where your choice makes
a difference that you're your will has a
place in the larger context and that and
then then faith is this sense of like
being held in surfing it literally is
called being in the pocket right yeah
yeah literally be to know how to sense
what's happening around you and to
respond to what's happening in a way
that you are held in the pocket it's a
very wu-wei sensibility right right
that's what I'm talking about in that
direction okay that's very much in line
with what I was thinking when I was
trying to propose this idea of this
dynamic sense of continuity of contact
with an unfolding process which of
course is exactly what's happening in
the surf law and then there's you
brought in an extra dimension which you
often do wonderfully with your with your
visualizations I love the way you do
that by the way you will be articulating
something conceptually you'll bring it
into a visual metaphor and then the
visual metaphor unfolds unpacking
something in the phenomenology that
isn't immediately referenced in the
concept because you brought up this idea
of like the pocket and finding the sweet
spot right it's nice to talk to you
again by the way it's been too long yeah
I agree
I like it a lot too and so I like that
I'd like iiiii cuz you know you know
being a martial artist Tai Chi Chuan and
stuff like that they're like it's part
of its of course getting into a flow
State
but part of its also getting into like
you said getting into the pocket so I
take it that like there's there there's
a there's a normativity to faith if
you'll allow me like you can do it you
can do it better or worse you can think
of the surfer you know maintaining sort
of a continuity of contact with the wave
but they're sort of clumsy right and
then you the one who gets if you'll
allow me a tournament been working on
you know gets an optimal grip on the
situation right and they find that
reciprocity with the worlds right
there's that deep sort about one minute
and then they have a sense of right and
it's not something you know even with
the power of a skill I would say that
it's a knowing at a much deeper level
you you know that you you you have this
sense of a deep kind of conformity and
at one MIT with things that yeah gives
you the sense that you're in you're in
that sweet spot with respect to how
something is unfolded is that part of
what you're putting your finger on yeah
absolutely I really like the fact that
you highlight that notion of n1 men
because it is different my first-person
experience when I'm in the circumstances
I guess that sense that sense of sort of
being and dropping away and an extension
and a sensitivity and you know and of
course the classic example is that the
moment that you are aware of it or
you're thinking about it or you get in
your head you're not in it anymore right
and that's important right in the
context of this notion of propositional
well that's exactly right so there's two
things I want to talk about there one is
exactly that because I'm really
interested as you know and dialectic and
how it affords deal logos I'm interested
in about this this you know this
interplay between dropping in I'll use
your metaphor it's it's a good one and
then maybe I'll use my metaphor stepping
back and looking at and right and that
there's a kind of higher order place you
can get there - yes that's got its own
sweet spot right absolutely yeah
absolutely completely in fact you're
again I just had the first-person
experience so there's like a middle spot
it's a bad place the drop shot of both
and there's this really interesting
thing where you're like actually in both
of those places and they really do
support each other yes yes and that's
the kind of faith in dialectic that you
see in the Platonic dialogues I'm
reading a really good book I kept naming
the name of the author's name starts
with an R I'll call Sookie I think I
might be getting it wrong it's a
Heidegger's Platonism guy sent it to me
and he's unpacking this whole thing that
because Plato thought that ultimately
there's a deep kind of faith in
dialectic and Plato because and
confederal argues that when you're doing
this process you altima can't put it
into words which sounds odd for
dialectic right but his whole point is
you you do this so something catches
fire right that is ultimately non
propositional but nevertheless that
doesn't mean you can just do whatever
you want there is a normativity there is
there is this there is this guiding
massive a yeah yeah yeah yeah again
Haig's absolutely disputed it's
beautiful it's like you could say maybe
even like am hmm this new ship of
conformity that there's a shape there is
a shape to it there is a shape that's
all there is to it maybe if you know if
you don't grab a ball like this then you
were not going to be successful in
holding the ball like if you hold it
like this it's gonna slide up your hand
was that yeah that's the optimum of
gripping again the dynamic yeah the more
gripping so that brings me to kind of
the other other point I wanted to we
don't have to get to it immediately but
I want to try and situate that in terms
of again the religion that's not a
religion this idea because I want to add
one more dance to it absolutely very
powerful and I'm seeing it unfold in
real time actually okay great because
the one more thing I would want to add
to that which i think is implicit
especially if the surfer right is
getting an optimal grip on a continually
shifting situation is the surfer is also
going through some kind of transfer
process now in the surfing situations
its transformation of theirs but their
skillset in their sensitivity but what
we're talking about I think when we're
talking about the religion that's not a
religion is a much more profound and
comprehensive transformation and so what
I mean is for discussion is taking this
notion we're starting to craft of faith
but then saying but what does that look
like when it's a faith that's gonna take
you through this much more comprehensive
and profound transformation does it does
that make sense as a question yeah
absolutely let me just try throw
something out that occurs to me and I
apologize that this is a little bit too
topical but yeah I'm gonna use the
coronaviruses or the no that's the
unfolding medic crisis as I'm referring
to it because you have to think about a
lot of stuff besides just a virus yeah
in this context of faith in this context
of religion yeah and it's really quite
fascinating actually it's almost like a
mirror reflection of the Black Plague
yes you and I talked about this last
time yeah yeah so here's here's what's
going to happen at least in some places
in some context is that some people will
take faith in this sense that we're
talking about that's just to say that
they will find a way to come into a how
do you say it a dynamic conformity yeah
yeah with what is really unfolded yeah
which we should say that they will make
good choices they will they will make
choices that are right in relationship
to the reality that they find themselves
in and to who they are aren't the place
that they are at in relationship to
themselves to their own bodies to to the
people who they are with the
relationships that they are near and and
in fact in extending it and if you find
out whether this is happening in real
time for example in many many
communities around the world or the
beginning to realize that a lot of the
help that they need we'll only in
candolyn be found among the people who
they are nearby right and to the degree
to which you and what I'm saying is it
that's actually a discovery of what is
in fact actually real mm-hmm that's a
reality it is simply the reality that in
a context like this to be able to rely
on your neighbors is a very a good
strategy it's a good place to be yeah
and to be able to be relied on by your
neighbors is a good place to be yes just
remember we're not trivial yet all these
things exactly good faith competence
integrity trustworthiness all these sort
of things that are old-school virtues
for good reasons as our friend Jordan
Peterson sort of famously tried to
hammer into the consciousness hmm that
is a coming to faith thread that
building of an actual capacity to do so
all right now it's not the hope that it
exists but the learning the relearning
and the many ways does the rediscovery
of what it means to be able to have
integrity and what it means to be able
to have trustworthiness and and and how
to do so across a larger group of people
how to be how to be a neighbor to be
neighborly and to be a good neighbor in
the context of crisis is an embodiment
of this faith that we're talking about
in in a larger fashion I'm on a larger
body and the the beautiful thing about
the environment they're in right now is
that it has this beautiful that the the
constants between salience and relevance
we are forced to make choices yeah we
find out very quickly whether the basis
of choice was a good basis of choice
right right it has meaning it lands
right there are consequences yes so this
is a very this is sort of an optimal
learning environment for for building
faith I'm really enjoying this by the
way I really like the idea of being able
to recover this this notion so well so
deeply from the false narrative that has
presented it as being kind of maximally
maladaptive